Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection - Library Special Collections, ca. 1198-1616
UCLA Library Special Collections
Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection - Library Special Collections
ca. 1198-1616
medspeci
Ferrari, Mirella.
This finding aid lists the Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts holdings of the Department of Special Collections as cited in Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts at the University of California, Los Angeles (1991), compiled by Mirella Ferrari and edited by R.H. Rouse (Call Number - Z6621 C123m 1991). The catalog identifies the contents, illumination, physical makeup, binding, and provenance for all Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts in the UCLA library system. These manuscripts can be found in the Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library's History and Special Collections Division, the John E. Anderson Graduate School of Management Library's Robert E. Gross collection of Rare Books in Business and Economics, the Music Library's Hathaway Collection, and UCLA Library Special Collections. The various Indexes are brief lists of all manuscripts in the UCLA library system while the Container List consists only of the holdings in UCLA Library Special Collections.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF. Advance notice is required for access to the collection. Please contact UCLA Library Special Collections for paging information.
History
The present catalog, begun over a decade ago, stands at the beginning of modern cataloging of medieval manuscripts in North America. Its completion may serve as the occasion to pause for a moment and examine the beginnings and progress to date of manuscript cataloging in America, as well as to offer some comment on what it has taught us and how best to continue.1
By “modern” cataloging is meant the writing of catalogs that can stand comparison with those of European national collections, such as the catalog of the Prussian State Library by Rose, that of the Royal Collection in the British Library by Warner and Gilson, the still-growing catalog of the Latin manuscripts at the Bibliothéeque nationale, and the catalogs of various portions of the Vatican Library, such as the Vaticani latini by Pelzer and Ruysschaert and the Reginenses by Wilmart.2 These works distinguish themselves from earlier catalogs by the fact that they involve extensive research into the identity of the contents, illumination, physical makeup, binding, and provenance of the manuscripts they describe.
The manuscript collections of North America are at the same time substantial and dispersed. In this they are no different from the collections of any European country, save in degree: Europe's collections are larger, North America's collections more widely dispersed. Institutional cataloging of the great collections in Europe has moved at a slow but assured pace. Cataloging of smaller collections has been largely haphazard. In Germany after World War II, at the urging of Bernhard Bischoff the program for catalogs of state libraries was begun, providing scholars with modern catalogs of the libraries of Frankfurt, Stuttgart, and Nurnberg, among others. In England, N.R. Ker saw the cataloging of undescribed manuscripts in small collections as a major desideratum, and undertook to do it himself. Ker was part of that generation of English medievalists, formed in the 1930s, who shared a belief in the importance of the written page and who, when something needed doing, got up and did it. To them, knowledge of the medieval past lay in an understanding of its surviving manuscripts and, therefore, these were to be sought out and cataloged; order, in the form of bibliographic control, was gradually to be imposed upon chaos. This message was firmly transmitted to anyone who listened. Following in the footsteps of M.R. James, any scholar possessed of reasonable curiosity would find an interesting collection of manuscripts to describe. R.A.B Mynors explored Bishop Gray's manuscripts in Balliol College; Malcolm Parkes described the liturgical manuscripts at Keble College; and Ian Doyle with Alan Piper is cataloging the manuscripts of Bishop Cosin's library in Durham.3 In California also, cataloging began as an individual effort, involving a number of scholars working in undescribed, isolated, and largely overlooked collections.
At the first and simplest level was the undertaking by Dennis Dutschke, and later also by Consuelo Dutschke, of a general survey of manuscripts on the West Coast, ranging from Mount Saint Angel Abbey in Oregon to the San Diego Public Library. The initial intent was to present the results of the survey as a handlist, but in time the Dutschkes agreed that only a more thorough examination of the manuscripts would be of valid service to the academic community.
The author of the present catalog, Mirella Ferrari, a member of the faculty of Classical Philology at the Università cattolica del Sacro cuore in Milan, was brought to UCLA in the spring quarter of 1977 by the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies to catalog the medieval and renaissance manuscripts then in the university's libraries. Her mentor, Giuseppe Billanovich, who had spent a term at UCLA as visiting professor, had seen the body of uncataloged manuscripts and recommended to Fredi Chiappelli, then director of the Center, that Ferrari be invited for the task.
The opportunity to have a knowledgeable manuscript scholar as a colleague at UCLA and to assist her in whatever way possible with the library and the manuscripts was a great stimulus to catalog locally in Southern California and, in turn, to encourage cataloging in American collections generally. Ferrari delayed her return to Italy, and in the summer of 1977 she, Consuelo Dutschke, and I began with the Claremont Libraries, which housed the very sort of interesting but hitherto ignored collection endemic to the United States. Much of the summer went to the task. Undertaken at our own expense as an enjoyable experiment without deadlines or semi-annual progress reports, the catalog, frequently set aside when more urgent things came along, was finally completed and published in 1986, as the first volume in a series devoted to catalogs of manuscripts in California institutional libraries both private and public.4
In the late 1960s and '70s, with the prospect of the computer on the horizon, the production of a second supplement to De Ricci's Census 5 was frequently put forward as a worthy undertaking at meetings of the Medieval Academy's Standing Committee for Centers and Regional Associations (CARA). From the enormous effort it had cost W.H. Bond to produce the first supplement to De Ricci, however, it was obvious that the obstacles lying in the way of such a large undertaking made these suggestions impracticable. For one person, working for a research center or alone, however well equipped with research assistants, to catalog not only the new acquisitions of the Morgan, the Beinecke, and the Houghton but also the numerous uncataloged manuscripts in smaller out-of-the-way collections of manuscripts scattered across America, was impossible unless the researcher wanted to consecrate a lifetime to this task—which usually turned out not to be the case. An application to the NEH with the blessing of the Academy was the customarily preferred solution to the problems of financial support. There was a firm conviction in those heady days that a combination of graduate research assistants, computers, and NEH funding could produce manuscript descriptions. The essential missing ingredient, the broadly learned and well-trained cataloger willing to slog away at this task for years on end, was seldom mentioned. There were capable people on the scene, but the older among them already had too many irons in the fire to allow them to begin again, while younger scholars would have been ill advised to invest much effort on catalogs given that manuscript cataloging unfortunately counted little in hiring or tenure decisions. America did not and does not have a tax-funded Federal Academy of Sciences, like France's Centre national de recherche scientifique or West Germany's Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, to support a cadre of full-time catalogers.
What was needed was a means of encouraging able younger scholars with secure positions to catalog defined collections in their own universities. The way to do this was to create a community of catalogers, who would work individually on collections of their choice with the support of the Endowment, who would share their knowledge and areas of first-hand observation with other catalogers, and who together would establish standards through practical experience. The human factor, the quality and motivation of the individual cataloger, was most important.
In the 1970s, the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) became interested in developing programs to make collections of primary sources in North America better known Margaret Childs, then director of the Research Tools Program, expressed an interest in supporting the cataloging of manuscript collections. The first large collection to be described with NEH support was the Huntington Library, which had applied in 1974 for a grant to prepare guides to its extensive and varied manuscript collections. Its curator of manuscripts Jean Preston left in 1977 for Princeton, and the new curator Mary Robertson sought advice on the guide to the medieval manuscripts. Consuelo Dutschke of UCLA was invited to prepare the catalog, even though it would mean putting off completion of the Claremont catalog for a number of years. Dutschke's catalog of the medieval manuscripts at the Huntington appeared in two volumes in 1989, Shortly after the Huntington catalog was under way, the Endowment awarded the Newberry Library a grant to catalog its medieval manuscripts, the project to be carried out by Paul Saenger. The Newberry adopted the format for description that had been developed for the Claremont and Huntington catalogs, and Consuelo Dutschke and I served as editorial consultants. The major East Coast libraries also benefited from NEH-supported cataloging. In 1982, Barbara Shailor was awarded the first in a series of NEH grants to catalog the manuscripts of the Beinecke Library at Yale, a task begun by Cora Lutz in 1969. The Endowment's Research Tools Program under Margaret Childs was again instrumental in seeing that the catalog would adopt the format for description employed in the other cataloging projects that the Program funded, and Consuelo Dutschke and I again served as editorial consultants. More recently, the Houghton Library of Harvard University, at the initiative of Larry Dowler (formerly of the Beinecke Library), undertook to catalog its medieval manuscripts. Laura Light of UCLA was selected as cataloger, and after a time the Library was granted NEH support. Barbara Shailor, Consuelo Dutschke, and I have served as editorial consults. Dutschke is now cataloging the manuscripts of the Bancroft Library, Berkeley, with NEH support. The Bancroft catalog will form the third volume in the present series of catalogs of medieval manuscripts in California institutions.6
The detailed cataloging of manuscripts with NEH support was not limited to manuscripts in America, but was already being applied to American collections of microfilms of manuscripts in European libraries. In the late 1960s, the Hill Monastic Manuscript Library of St. John's University in Minnesota decided to catalog, as well as to microfilm. As the member of the External Advisory Board familiar with cataloging, I worked with the catalogers, Donald Yates and later Hope Mayo, in devising a format for describing manuscripts from microfilm. Catalogs of the manuscripts of Herzogenburg and Tarragona have been published. The Ambrosiana Microfilm Library at the Medieval Institute, University of Notre Dame, in 1980 embarked on a catalog of the filmed Ambrosiana manuscripts, with NEH support and an able cataloging team headed by Christine Eder and later Donald Yates. Leonard Boyle OP and I served as advisors, and the cataloging format adopted was that which had been successfully employed by Yates at the Hill Library. The dismantling of that project by Ralph McInerney, then director of the Institute, was a great loss. The catalog project has recently been resuscitated by Louis Jordan, and volumes have begun to appear.7
Not all modern cataloging in America found its origins in the community of catalogers described above. The first catalog of an American collection done in modern form was begun in 1982 by Lilian Randall at the Walters Art Gallery in Baltimore, with the support of the Kress Foundation and NEH. Randall, whose first volume appeared in 1989, brought both Barbara Shailor and me into contact with the Walters project, and she adopted a format similar to that used in the NEH-supported catalogs described above. In 1980, the Library of Congress decided to prepare a catalog of its medieval manuscripts.
The project, supported by the Library rather than by NEH, has, nevertheless, also been in informal contact with various of the catalogers mentioned above, in particular Donald Yates, Lilian Randall, and me, and has followed something of the basic format of description adopted by the NEH catalogs. The first volume, by Svato Schutzner, appeared in 1989.8 These catalogs are a testimony to the cooperation of scholars, libraries, and the federal government.
From time to time it has been suggested that the community of scholars who catalog manuscripts develop a model format for description. An agreed-upon form would simplify the National Endowment's work and ensure a certain standard and uniformity of description. While this is an appealing notion, it has been resisted, and rightly so, for several reasons. As manuscripts are each unique items, a degree of flexibility is required in the way they are to be described. A fixed format, like a form to be filled in, tends to make one force the manuscript to fit the format. The form of N.R. Ker's descriptions is constantly adapted to suit the needs of the manuscript being described; for Ker, practicality and common sense overruled system and consistency every time. Catalogers, also, are each unique people who bring to their task specific insights, the expression of which should be allowed. Lastly, to establish a format for description inevitably freezes the format; it implies that we have determined the best way of describing what we see, and it is doubtful that this is so. There are a number of areas where the method of description will change, one hopes for the better. The cataloger's treatment of a manuscript's illumination and decoration has changed from being largely ignored, to being described as part of the physical make-up on a par with the dimensions and number of columns, to now receiving a separate section of its own. At present the treatment of binding fragments in a catalog description appears sometimes with the contents, sometimes in the binding section. The increased use of photographs to supplement words will certainly influence the form of future descriptions. Each of the American catalogs mentioned in this essay is based on the same basic model, yet each has adapted the model in one way or another to suit the specific situation.
To catalog in depth has always required serious justification. Libraries and funding agencies ask, why spend three years describing 150 manuscripts when a brief contents list of the 150 could be prepared in six months? For the most part, American manuscript collections are not large enough to make this a serious problem. Both Consuelo Dutschke and Barbara Shailor have cataloged collections of 350 and 500 manuscripts in a reasonable time. The question itself, however, is poorly put, since it implies that one must choose one or the other, catalog or handlist. In fact, what one wants for massive collections such as the Hill Monastic Manuscript Library or the large European libraries, is both. A short-form inventory of known contents, rapidly produced, on-line so as to be constantly updatable, will satisfy the basic needs of users. The inventory can be followed by the in-depth research catalog moving at its own pace.
National organizations of archivists and rare book librarians at present are expressing increasing interest in establishing a format for an on-line system of cataloging manuscripts. For the most part, these organizations are concerned with box-level descriptions of papers and, on occasion, modern bound manuscripts, where problems of identifying the contents are minimal and materials can be cataloged without leaving one's desk. The system under consideration, however, would theoretically be competent to receive indexable descriptions of any type of manuscript—including medieval documents and bound volumes. To date, no cataloger of medieval and renaissance manuscripts nor, indeed, any other medieval or renaissance scholar has been asked to participate in such a project. One hopes that situation will change—that those who catalog medieval and renaissance manuscripts will be consulted about the problems encountered in preparing descriptions, and that students of the Middle Ages and Renaissance will be asked what information they hope to find in a description. Data banks and on-line access hold great promise, but only if the information that goes into them is produced by competent and informed people. This is a time when the relationship between librarian and scholar needs to be one of interested and active cooperation, rather than protectionism and mutual exclusion.9
America has an abundance of medieval and renaissance manuscripts dispersed in numerous libraries across the country. Some libraries such as the J. Pierpont Morgan, the Houghton, and the Beinecke contain a thousand or more bound manuscripts. Others contain from several hundred to just a handful, and many contain only one manuscript or a few leaves. The manuscript holdings of the majority of these libraries have never been accurately described. This is in large part because the holdings are not substantial enough to permit the libraries in question to support curators of early manuscripts, and because accurate description requires specialized training in languages, scripts, textual history, art history, binding, and the history of collections, which neither general rare book librarians nor general medievalists have. Today, only four American institutions—the Beinecke Library, the Walters Gallery, the Morgan Library, and the Getty Museum—have curators of medieval and renaissance manuscripts. In addition, few manuscript librarians in American libraries, even the curators in the four institutions named above, can afford the time, above and beyond their normal curatorial duties, to engage in detailed cataloging of their collections. American librarians have been able to do little more than register the acquisition of medieval materials in the accession file, using information supplied by the bookseller. While this may be adequate for printed books (though it eliminates the recording of copy-specific information), it is not satisfactory for medieval and renaissance manuscripts, since too many book dealers, Sotheby's descriptions excepted, provide at best a rudimentary identification of the contents, often repeated from the previous dealer's description and not infrequently misleading. The establishment of national on-line data bases like RLIN does not solve the dilemma either, because a manuscript must first be cataloged by a competent scholar before there is accurate data to enter. This situation is not unique to medieval and renaissance manuscripts; it must exist to one degree or another in any area—e.g., oriental literature, history of science—that requires specialized knowledge.
The prospect for bibliographic control is particularly dim in the case of the library, no matter how large, that has only one or two manuscripts. An item alone, without a context in which to be used, is generally ignored: For example, the State Historical Society of Wisconsin possesses a large and remarkable thirteenth-century Bible, which had belonged to a Midwestern farm family for over a century before it was given to the Society; the University of British Columbia has one medieval manuscript, a fifteenth-century copy of Cicero's Prior Academics; Los Angeles Public Library has an early thirteenth-century manuscript of Peter Comestor's Bible history; and Pasadena Public Library had, until it was stolen in 1984, a fifteenth-century Rouen book of hours, which was one of six Rouen horae available for comparative study in Greater Los Angeles.10
This problem, that medieval and renaissance manuscripts are broadly scattered among libraries unequipped and unstaffed to deal with them, makes cataloging uniquely difficult in America. The solution, cataloging done by manuscript scholars, can be sought in two ways. One solution lies in the willingness and ability of the library to enlist the cooperation of subject specialists from among its university faculty, scholars who have a vivid interest in the rare books and manuscripts of a given field. The benefits of such cooperation can be seen in the example of Cornell University, where the late George Healey, Professor of English Literature and distinguished Wordsworth bibliographer, was named curator of the university's Wordsworth Collection and then Curator of Rare Books, Many North American universities both public and private have on their faculties—whether in English literature, art history, classics, or history—scholars interested in and capable of developing a manuscript collection for research and study. They are a resource for librarians to draw on in developing university collections in the most effective way. In other cases, where the faculty interest is lacking, the appropriate solution would be cataloging by external scholars, funded by either the holding library or the National Endowment. In this fashion, the medieval and renaissance manuscripts in American libraries can be cataloged, and the scholarship of research catalogers, following in the footsteps of Wilmart and Ker, can be properly valued by their fellow medieval and renaissance scholars.
Perhaps the time will come for an idea once considered but dismissed as premature: appealing to the Endowment or another agency to fund a program which would provide three years' support to a set number of postdoctoral scholars to attend a summer institute in manuscript description and then to catalog a collection of manuscripts in their home state. A group of experienced specialists in liturgy, illumination, canon law, and other specific areas including vernacular languages would be available for consultation. The descriptions would be entered in a single data bank which would in time become the central record (catalog) of manuscripts in American collections. An editorial team would review descriptions and assist in seeing the published volumes through the press in a national catalog series which would replace De Ricci and the Supplement and which could be periodically updated from its computer base. If this or something similar is done, I trust that one will have learned from the catalogs described above that the scholarly value of the descriptions produced depends almost entirely on the quality of the cataloger.